<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second supply to the draft of a great act or system, concerning the regulation of the law. Or, A fall of above twenty nine in thirty writts of error and of nine parts in ten of the charge, in those after to be necessary : and a prevention of delays, inconveniences, and mischeifs in future, which formerly have happened by such writs : In order to the saving yearly to the people many thousands of pounds, part of the severall millions and odd of pounds by the Anti-Levellers Antidote mentioned to be saved. With a short justification of the funerall of tythes of impropriators and symonists, &amp;c. Rejoyned unto by an angry pamphlet, intituled, A vindication of a short treatise of tythes, &amp;c. / Published by those who published the Funerall, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05779</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617443</idno>
  <idno type="VID">175366</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240883701</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2335A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">51617443</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2730:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second supply to the draft of a great act or system, concerning the regulation of the law. Or, A fall of above twenty nine in thirty writts of error and of nine parts in ten of the charge, in those after to be necessary : and a prevention of delays, inconveniences, and mischeifs in future, which formerly have happened by such writs : In order to the saving yearly to the people many thousands of pounds, part of the severall millions and odd of pounds by the Anti-Levellers Antidote mentioned to be saved. With a short justification of the funerall of tythes of impropriators and symonists, &amp;c. Rejoyned unto by an angry pamphlet, intituled, A vindication of a short treatise of tythes, &amp;c. / Published by those who published the Funerall, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Suggested publication data from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and cropped with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the California State Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Writ of error --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175366:1"/>
            <head>A SECOND SUPPLY To the Draft of a great Act or Cystem, concerning the Regulation of the LAW.</head>
            <head type="sub">OR, A fall of above twenty nine in thirty Writts of Error: And of nine parts in ten of the charge, in those after to be necessary: And a prevention of Delays, Inconveniencies, and Mischeifes in future, which formerly have happened by such Writs: In order to the saving yearly to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple many thousands of pounds, part of the severall Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions and odd of pounds by the <hi>Anti-Levellers Antidote</hi> mentioned to be saved.</head>
            <head type="sub">WITH <hi>A short Justification of the Funerall of Tythes of Impropriators and Symonists,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">Rejoyned unto by an angry Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>A Vindication of a short Treatise of Tythes,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by those who published the</hi> Funerall, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as very many <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Error</hi> have bin brought and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by divers unconscionable and turbulent persons, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for delay of <hi>Execution,</hi> upon divers Judgments and Recoveries, which for just and due Debts and demands they have knowne have been recovered and obtained against them, and have by Combination with Town-Clerks and Stewards, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Courts, procured the Records thereof; with very many Continual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and other unnecessary things to be returned with, and upon the Returne of such <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> after that the prosecutors of such <hi>Writs</hi> have caused delay of the <hi>Executions</hi> of such Judgements or Recoveries, sometimes by one, two, or three Renuings of such <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> contrived by Officers for their owne onely gaines, by meanes whereof divers and sundry Plaintiffs and Demandants, and Recoverers of Judgments and Recoveries, have beene at more charge to repaire to superiour Courts, to which such Records have been
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175366:2"/>sent or removed, then the matter therein recovered hath been worth, though such prosecutors before mentioned, of such <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> sometimes have been at double, other times trebble so much, rather then they would or have payd, that (which in conscience they have knowne) they ought to have payd.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Matter upon many of such VVrits of Error after the returne thereof into superiour Courts, hath there long depended before the same have been determined, and much trouble and charge hath been about the same in some of them, more then the thing recovered hath been of value, which chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath been occasioned by Contrivances of extorting and exacting Officers for their filthy lucre.</p>
            <p>And whereas in ancient times VVritts of Error (as appeares by the forme thereof, in the Register Book of VVritts) were made out upon the Complaint of the Parties grieved by any erronious Judgement, or Recovery, and were drawn by the Learned Master Clerks of the <hi>Chancery,</hi> till by them a forme was contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for many of those VVrits: And now of late Those of them which have been ordinary VVritt or VVrits of course have been made of course by Cursitors, and all those (which since those ancient Times have been speciall) have been drawn and contrived by learned Counsell and Clerks, and coppies thereof deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to <hi>Cursitors</hi> to make, who have not only taken so much as in competency hath been sufficient for the drawing thereof, but also as much more as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors of the same have paid for drawing and contriving thereof, to those who could draw and have drawne those speciall VVritts, whereby the Prosecutors of such VVrits have been put to double charge to pay unto the Undeserving and Ignorant more then to the deserving, Diligent, and Learned.</p>
            <p>For Remedy wherof, it is wished to be desired that it may be provided.</p>
            <p>That hereafter no stay of Execution shall be by reason of any VVritt of Error above six weeks next after my Judgement shall be given, or Recovery had, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the Prosecutor or Prosecutors of such Writts, do set down and expresse plainely in writing the Tenor of the whole Record of such Iudgement or Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, or so much thereof, wherein Hee, Shee, or they, do or shall shew the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or Errors to be, in the manner and forme of a Suggestion, or a Bill or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, without vaine Recitalls or Repetitions of vaine and frivilous continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances or other things, wherein no Error be, or shall be shewed or assigned.</p>
            <p>And that no Writt of <hi>Supersedeas,</hi> upon any Writ of Error hereafter shall be made, untill such Suggestion, Bill, or Complaint be, or shall be so drawn, and Error or Errors set down or expressed as farre, and as many, as the Prosecutor, or Prosecutors in such Writ do, will or shall insist upon; and the same be, or shall be signed under the hand of one or more of the Iudges or Iustices of the Court pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to reforme, or correct such Errors or, false Iudgements, and to reverse or affirme such Iudgement or Recovery (expressing therein by such Iudge or Iustice, that he conceiveth Error to be in some part thereof.</p>
            <p>And that mediatly after any Defendant in such Writ of Error, door shall heare of such Errors assigned, Hee, Shee, or They may plead to the same, and after issue ioyned thereupon, either upon such Record or Tenor thereof, the Judges or Justices of such Court, shall and may proceed to the affirming, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall of such Judgement, or Recovery only, upon those Errors so assigned, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> shewed, or to be assigned or shewed, and none other; and award and make out Writts of Execution or Restitution accordingly.</p>
            <p>And that after such <hi>Suggestion,</hi> Bill, or Complaint be or shall be so signed by such Judge or Justice, any Counsell or Clerk who can and will at the cheapest Rate, may make such Writt of Error.</p>
            <p>At that imediately after the making thereof, the same with the said Suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Bill, or complaint, shall be delivered into the Court, proper to heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175366:2"/>the same, together also with a true Copy thereof for the Defendant or Defendants, who do or shall appear to the same.</p>
            <p>And that instantly after such Defendant or Defendants do or shall appear, and Plead or Answer to the same Hee, Shee, or they shall leave for the Prosecutor or Prosecutors of such VVritt, a true copy of such plea or Answer in the same Court.</p>
            <p>If thus, or in this Manner, and a Paper called an Abatement of Motions and Orders, &amp;c. formerly published, it should be Provided, then neither would, or could such Infinits of Appeales be, as inevitably would happen; in case such Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales (as in the said Court, Act, or Systeme is expressed) should fall out to be enacted.</p>
            <p>And besides many People by such VVritts of Error, would be righted, in Causes, which amount not to above the value of 10. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> or 30. <hi>l.</hi> alwayes falling out to be very many and more then all others; wherein they would by the <hi>Cystem,</hi> if Writs of Errors should be quite taken away, as is mentioned in that <hi>Cystem;</hi> every one thereby (who shall bring such Writts of Error) being first enjoyned to leave ten pound in the Registers Office of the Chancery, which many people neither are, or are like to be able to do; but must be constrained to undergo any wrong Carriage in their Cause, by reason of their Inability to seek Reliefe therein: Therefore such Appeales are like to endanger a great Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry among them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A stort Justification of the funerall of Tythes, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>HAving within two or three dayes last past happened upon a <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> called <hi>A Vindication</hi> of a short <hi>Treatise</hi> of Tythes; excepted against the <hi>Funerall of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Impropriations and Tyths,</hi> being scattered abroad lately fince the last Trinity Terme, in the nature of a Rejoynder, to a Reply of ours, to an other Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet called a <hi>Treatise</hi> of Tythes, touching angerly, and snatching at, by way of Answer, to a small Tract of Tyths of Friends of us, only catching hold at some things in it to undervalue the same; and leaping over the most materiall things in it; Wee have thought it convenient to sur-reioyne to that Reioynder, and by way of Sur-reioynder do say to the Matters of that Reioynder: Fist as to that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter where he saith, that it is said, that we in our Reply say, that there is not any of the learned Hystories, but question the duty of payment of Tithes; as is true they have said, to such as of late have taken the same: which one of those Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories hath branded, as sacriligious and Church Robbers, and so it is, as he might have found in the Tract, pag. 31. 32 and to that which the party reioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing saith, that he who saith, the Labourer is worthy of his hire, and thou shalt not muzzle the Oxe that treadeth out the <hi>Corno;</hi> we say that such Tyth-takers as the Tract and our Reply speak of, that is to say, the Impropriators be not any such, as so labour, but as they be at large expressed in the Tract pag. 30, 31, 32, and rather tread the Corne into the Myre, then do any good, and therefore such unprofitable Cattell ought to be <hi>muzzled.</hi> And therefore the Reioynant had better for himselfe have forborne that Assertion; for which (when his Clients the Impropriators shall come to understand it) they will not commend him for the same, being it maketh cleerly against them? And the party reioning saith, that the Writers say, that it is the Rise, the part and Manner of payment that troubles them all; which true is, and very well they may, by reason of the great and exces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive parts of the poor Husband-mans corne; which the moddern Tyth takers, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Impropriators for doing no good, have swept away, as is it at large expressed in the Tract, <hi>p.</hi> 36. And the Reioynder further saith. That it is not a Tyth, or portion thereof to be due unto the Minister, that troubles those, that have written of that subiect, by which word <hi>Portion</hi> may be observed, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Tyths, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175366:3"/>from ours in these moddern Times; therefore by his owne confession, how in reason can hee desire that the payment thereof should continue as it hath done? But the partie Reioyning is so subtill as to ioyne the Ministers with the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators. And because we acknowledge they acknowledge they have been due to the Ministers rather then the Impropriators, and that a competent Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ought in conscience and Reason to be allowed to the learned and Godly Ministers. He bringeth the same for the vindicating the payment of Tyth to Impropriators: which whether any of the learned or Godly Ministry have cause to give him thanks for, any reasonable man may Judge: And besides it may be observed all along in the Treatise, and Vindication, how iniuriously they would make the Ministers (as it were) a stalking horse for their further help to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their beloved <hi>Avarice</hi> of Tythes without desert. And where in the Reioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he saith, that the reply doth condemne the Appropriators for the deteyning the Tenth and Tythes, as they are paid in his Nation; which well it may, as it saith, it doth the Impropriators, for their Predecessors the Appropriators were in respect of Tythes to afford sufficient maintenance for the <hi>Vicar</hi> and <hi>Poore</hi> as is said in the Tract 36. and Reply, and as is enacted 15. <hi>R.</hi> 2.2.6.4 <hi>H.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               <p>And King <hi>H.</hi> the 8. had them no otherwise then the <hi>Abbots</hi> and <hi>Monaches,</hi> &amp;c. the Appropriators had the same, as any may see in the Statutes of King <hi>H.</hi> 8. concerning the same. And we deny them to have come to the Impropriators any otherwayes by any setled Law of this Nation (it being confessed in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder that neither the <hi>Decretal</hi> Epistle of <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, in the yeare 1200. nor the Counsell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> in the yeare 1215. could impose Tithes upon the same.) And yet both the Treatise and the Vindication insist much upon the Great Charter, to be for the Right of the Church, being made not long after that Counsell, and no intervening Law, or Statute of this Nation, was made for Tithe, whereby it appeareth that the Vindication it selfe sheweth Tithes to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setled then: Therefore the great Charter maketh nothing at all for the Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators, but against them. And if they should go about to shew that any Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations were in those times, they are like to misse of finding of any. And let the Reioynant, or any of his Adherents come on againe, and they shall be sure to heare more from some of Us, to the further manifestation of the nullity of the Impropriators Right to Tithes, as it hath been lately found out, they have imployed the same.</p>
               <p>And we also deny that the People of this Nation, have held the payment of Tithes reasonable; Or that they have submitted to the payment of the same, any otherwayes then by threats, and being kept under, and in feare, by the power of the Proud of the Clergy unlawfully usurped, which was the principall Cause of frighting many of the People from contending with the Impropriators, who for the greatest part complyed with those, and climbed by their Ladder, both these and those for the most part having misimployed Tyths alike, as is mentioned in the Tract, <hi>pag.</hi> 31 <hi>Reply p.</hi> 1. but as for submittance in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the same to the Godly painfull and consciencious Minister, we neither, can, will or do deny. And it is well in the Reioynder to confesse that the most learned Writer mentioned in the Tract, doth shew a variety in payment of <hi>Tyth.</hi> And as to the practise of it mentioned to be in the Treatise <hi>p.</hi> 14. that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the abandoning of Charity by the <hi>Tith-takers</hi> and before such nonusing misu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing or dissusing as in severall places in the <hi>Tract,</hi> and in the Reply, and in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places in this Sur-reioynder be mentioned. And as to the Question in the Reioynder whose Officers or Stewards <hi>Receivers</hi> of <hi>Tyths</hi> were for their imployment to good uses, whose misuser, Non-user, or Dis-user thereof is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture thereof, whether Gods Stewards, to whom then saith the Party re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning, they are only accomptable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175366:3"/>imploy them to good uses as before is said, otherwise, do they not think God will put it into the Hearts of the Parliament to take the same from them, and leave the same to the Owners of the Lands, that they may be the better enabled to maintaine an able Ministry and the Poor for which uses they ought to go, as the Stewards and Officers of which Owners they are, as the <hi>Abbots</hi> were for convenient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Vicars, and reliefe of the poor, as appeareth by the Statutes of <hi>R.</hi> 2. and <hi>H.</hi> the 4. and so <hi>K.H.</hi> the 8. took them into his hands: and to, and for the same intent and purpose gave, conveyed, and disposed the Appropriations, at such small Rates as is mentioned in the Tract, being very little or nothing in respect of the rates as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lands were sold for in those times at the first, to such as were charitable and well imployed those Impropriatons. And besides the Party reioyning (shewing such cunningnesse in his writing) we think is not so ignorant (although as he truely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, as Gods Stewards (of that which we possesse in the World) we are, only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to him) but that yet the <hi>Reioynant</hi> may know, as it is commonly seen; when any Mildemeanour or other uniust Action is Committed, the Parties committing the same, are questionable by the <hi>Supreame Authority</hi> and Law: And of what dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous consequence his Misapplying of those Words are, is manifest; for thereby (if observed) all Government would be destroyed, and any unjust action committed, if the party doing the same might not be questioned for it.</p>
               <p>And where the Rejoynder saith, that the Parson is seized of the Tithes, &amp;c. in Right of his Church, as a man is said to be seized of his Lands in the right of his Wife, and yet it saith also that the man is not his Wives officer or Steward; but true and lawfull Owner and Possessor to his own use, but the <hi>Reioynant</hi> may know if he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that if the Husband commit any offence, whereby he shall be divorsed from his Wife, or he repudiat her without cause, he will be compelled to restore to her her Lands, and why not then the Impropriator for such misuser, Non-user, or Dif-user as is affirmed in the <hi>Repl. p.</hi> 2. (which may as well follow) to Owners of the Lands, and not to such Patrons as shall use <hi>Symony:</hi> for no doubt there is, but Patrons were Lords of Mannors at first, who had the disposall of all the Lands in the Parish, aswell as of the <hi>Advouson,</hi> and now they have parted with their Lands for valuable consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, can there be any reason or equity that the Lords or Patrons should present a <hi>Symonist</hi> to starve the Poore and share and devide the spoile with him, as is too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, as is at large mentioned in the Tract <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>Repl. p.</hi> 2. And in the Reioynder it is confessed that the Law hath or deyned to rectifie Lands, Tythes, &amp;c. given to good uses upon their misimployment: and why may it not now be put in practise being such misimployment is newly found out? the Reioynant alleadging also that <hi>Keeper ships</hi> of <hi>Wild-beasts, Stewards</hi> or <hi>Bienniall Cessation,</hi> &amp;c. Suit not with it: if it be in that point only of difference by being seised in their own right, or in the Right of the Church, or other Right, but be not such seised as well as Parsons? Yea as strong altogether, but that is nothing to the matter in Hand. And as to the Poors Lands mentioned in the <hi>Reioynders</hi> to remain to this day. We know of none, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we know many Parishes the Tythes whereof be impropriate, and have heard of very few Lands belonging to any Poore in any Parish; and if any had been set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon any Parish in such manner as is mentioned in the <hi>Reioynder,</hi> it is like they had remained to this day, for who should take or alyen them away? And they who look for any Vicars endowment or provision made for the Poore, shall finde no such thing in the Statutes which the <hi>Reioynant</hi> quoteth; and yet he saith, that we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that <hi>Endowment</hi> and <hi>Allowance</hi> in those Statutes was as the value of things then were equall or neer to the worth; although we have expressed in our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply</hi> no such Statutes at all, but as we in our Sur-reioynder have sayd, and now say further, by these Statutes it appeareth that <hi>Appropriators</hi> were to provide convenient maintenance for a Vicar and the Poor, which we do averr doth imply that they were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as it were) Officers or Stewards,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175366:4"/>and may forfeit, as before we sayd in our <hi>Reply, p.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>But he <hi>Reioynant</hi> demandeth the question, To whom they should be forfeit? and answereth we say to the Freeholders of the Lands: but he demandeth the Freehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Title to them, saying, He never bought nor payd for them: To which we say, the Freeholders bought the Lands with all appurtenances and profits, and as is sayd in the <hi>Tract. p.</hi> 33.34. why should not the Freeholders, as well as to be subiect to all incumbrances of losse, or impaire of his Lands, as also of hinderers, disturbers, and enemies, the most subtill of which be the Tyth-takers, as is expressed in the <hi>Tract. p.</hi> 33.34.</p>
               <p>And then the <hi>Reioynant</hi> saith, That we see it every day, the title of Appropriators to be by the Judges adiudged good: How untrue that is, that such thing hath been, or can be done so often, every reasonable man may imagine; but it seemeth he is some great Owner and Possessor of <hi>impropriations,</hi> and is like to say any thing, be it never so untrue, to uphold his <hi>Diana,</hi> if he could go smoothly away with it, and cloud the peoples Judgements.</p>
               <p>But if such Titles have been often adiudged good, he might have seene if he would, <hi>Reph.</hi> 2. where it is sayd, That such <hi>Mis-user, Non-user,</hi> or <hi>Dis-user,</hi> have not been stood upon, but it appeareth he is apt to catch and snatch at some things for his advantage, and leap over other things, as did the Writer of the <hi>Treatise;</hi> which if he had not done, or not mentioned some of the words in the <hi>Tract</hi> in an angry manner, his <hi>Treatise</hi> might have gone silent for ought we should have sayd to it, but left them both to be considered of by better Judgements.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Reioynant</hi> taxeth us with not having honourable thoughts of <hi>Supreme Authority:</hi> Although we never have had, did, nor doe intend to have ony other then honourable opinion of Supreme Authority, nor have any wayes declared o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise.</p>
               <p>And because it is sayd in the <hi>Tract, pag.</hi> 28. <hi>Reph.</hi> 4. That Tythe came to <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators</hi> at as low rates as Theif stolne goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to which the <hi>Treatise</hi> hath not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, and therefore the <hi>Reioynant</hi> by a wandering Answer, impertinent to the matter in hand, saith, That we cannot make the <hi>Appropriators</hi> Receivers, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the Parliaments theives: Doth this <hi>Reioynant</hi> deserve any commendations of the posterity of former Parliaments, to put the Theife upon them, and how may the future think of him? For we onely sayd that we conceived that if former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments had imagined how Tythes would have been vitiously used, they would not have made such Acts concerning the same as they have done, <hi>Rep. p.</hi> 3.4.5. <hi>Tr.</hi> 31. And we say in the <hi>Tract, p.</hi> 28. that at first the Tyth-takers might be charitable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then the custome of tything be good, but otherwise we say not good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be abolished, their foundation being sandy, as in <hi>Tract. p.</hi> 33. and the same being at first stolne by the Monks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is sayd in the <hi>Tract.</hi> 27. And why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may not then such things be pleaded in Bar, or given in Evidence, as in <hi>Tract. p.</hi> 26. and <hi>Reph p.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>After the <hi>Reinynant</hi> blameth us for answering the <hi>Treatise,</hi> where our Friends were charged with being as bad as <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apostate,</hi> who dispoyled the Church of their Livings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we onely saying, <hi>Rep.</hi> 4.6. that we thought the Tyth-takers, who were to maintaine the Vicar and Poor, as we have sayd before, and as the Statutes herein recited, and have not done the same, were more fit to have those uncharitable Titles put upon them then those our Freinds.</p>
               <p>And to his Question concerning the <hi>Lay-fees</hi> and <hi>Freehold</hi> of <hi>Tyth,</hi> we say, that what Hold soever any have, or can have to them, they are bound to the competent maintenance of the Minister and Poor, as we have sayd before.</p>
               <p>And as concerning the suffering of <hi>Recoveries,</hi> and levying of <hi>Fines,</hi> which he saith are daily done; but how he should know the same so often done, and how it is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175366:4"/>
               <p>But if such things have sometimes been done, we beleeve he can shew very few (if any) of tythes seperate from <hi>Rectories</hi> since the <hi>Impropriations</hi> thereof: concerning which if occasion be we can and shall say more hereafter.</p>
               <p>And after he saith, <hi>That when neither Judge nor Jury will comply with us, then,</hi> &amp;c. at which we well may and do admire he should say so, having as appeareth by his writing, taken notice of the <hi>Tract, Treatise,</hi> and <hi>Reply,</hi> since which no tryalls have been, wherein any such thing should come in question; and how true is that like to be which he alleadgeth, let every man Judge.</p>
               <p>And for the interruption of <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> as he mentioneth, we know of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done concerning this matter; therefore the <hi>Reioynant</hi> might have been silent, and not troubled himselfe with such things as he can know nothing of, unlesse he doth it to make stirr to no purpose; for we onely put our opinions out to publique view of those whom it most concerneth, few of us having any Lands, out of which tythe of corn hath been payd: And we advise the <hi>Replyant</hi> and his Adherents to take heed that he and they be not those, who go nearest to unsettlement and confusion of the Nation, in going away with Tythes for doing nothing, onely saying, they payd for them, but what was so payd, or at least at the first, they be loath to reveale. That both the <hi>Treatise</hi> and the <hi>Reioynder</hi> have slily leapt over.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Ministry,</hi> are not they beholding to him to put <hi>Superstition</hi> upon them? for it seemeth if the <hi>Impropriators</hi> can go on, the <hi>Reioynant</hi> careth not for them, therefore what reason have they to give him thanks?</p>
               <p>And <hi>Reioynder, p.</hi> 10. he cometh on againe with some Matter urged before and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, which he saith to be to proper uses, and yet he confesseth there, as we say too, as the <hi>Abbots, &amp;c</hi> held them, so they came to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and how that was may be seen in the Statutes aforesayd, as we have sayd before, which he saith he thinketh we have not read, but we doubt he hath not read them, or else over-read the same.</p>
               <p>And then he falleth on close with his <hi>Non claimes</hi> upon his <hi>Fines,</hi> and vaunteth as though he had us under his feet, and thunders against the Jurors to terrifie them; but if any <hi>Impropriators</hi> have any such Fines, they cannot be all sure of <hi>Non-claimes,</hi> but <hi>Claimes</hi> may be from five year to five year, for many years past, and some may be later, as the <hi>Non-user, Mis-user,</hi> or <hi>Dis-user</hi> have happened and been taken notice of, for what need or occasion can there be of any such thing before.</p>
               <p>And we advise him now he is or may be satisfied in conscience of the iust Right of Tythes that he be not troublesome nor self-conceited in opinion, that he can satisfie the Just and Learned Judges in their iudgements more then others, for they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge according to that which they see Right and Equity in their Judgements: and let him not endeavour to fright the honest Jurors, for they will not be assrighted by him, but go according to the iust right of their Evidence, say he what he will or can.</p>
               <p>It seemeth he is somewhat doubtfull of his this years Tythes, that his <hi>Reioynder</hi> cometh so warily out to intrench it selfe in the Countrey, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it selfe here, that it may not be rayled, or blown upon the Sand untill Harvest be past, but he may happen to faile in part.</p>
               <p>And then he condemneth us for want of charity (of which he and his adherents are most guilty, for the reasons, and as we have sayd before) and his reasons thereof are, because he saith, We propose nothing equivalent for the Appropriator: No not to all, for we need not, there will be sufficient to remaine to many of them, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much to others that have other great Possessions besides Tythes, out of which those that have no other maintenance may onely have some recompence, as we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sayd in our <hi>Reply, p.</hi> 3. at large, but it seemeth that he hath leapt over that, catching here and there at a peice to work upon for his owne use, as he hath in his <hi>Reioynder, p.</hi> 11. where he talketh concerning Heathenisme at a peice in the <hi>Tract,</hi> and misrepeated that, in saying the whole value, in stead of neer the value, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for doth it not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175366:5"/>in the <hi>Tract, p.</hi> 36. That a competent maintenance onely should be for the Ministry, and then sufficient would remaine to the Freeholder and Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man out of his Tythes to maintaine the Poor for his respective part, and that is for good uses, and not for Locusts and Caterpillers, as is sayd in the <hi>Tract, p.</hi> 30. And besides he might have seen in the <hi>Tract, p.</hi> 33.34. what benefit will accrue to the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder when the <hi>Vermin</hi> be rid from his Freehold: but that it seemeth the <hi>Reioynant</hi> would not repeat because as few as may be should take notice, who the most subtle of those Vermin be, to which we referr the Reader.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Reioynant</hi> finds fault for our wondring at some part of the <hi>Treatise,</hi> but now we may wonder at the matter in the <hi>Reioynder,</hi> where it is said, that he would have the Minister have his Tith till his Allowance begin: we say nothing against it till that be done; but we conceive the <hi>Reioynment</hi> little regardeth the Ministry, but to uphold the <hi>Diana</hi> of him and his Associats.</p>
               <p>And as for the Ministry if they had found any thing amisse against them, they could and would have answered for themselves, and we believe they never set the <hi>Reioynant</hi> at work, and he need not have medled with them, for rare it hath been for an <hi>Impropriator,</hi> to regard the Ministery. And as for the silenceing of us, or any Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of us, it is more then the <hi>Reioynant</hi> can do, if he go on any further in any thing which is not true and just.</p>
               <p>And in the Close he saith, he would have Truth vindicated, the Right of the Church, and propriety justified: but how farr he and his Associat or Adherent <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators,</hi> fall short of those things, most men that have dealing with them know, for as we have said before, do not they now withhould the maintenance of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry and the Church? And who can gainesay but that is the true right and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, and have not many of the Impropriators put the poore <hi>Vicar</hi> to dwell next their great Barnes, and keep themselves farre remote in obscurity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the poore <hi>Vicar</hi> having small allowance, and having had charitable minds, have been suddenly devoured by the Poore, Beggers and Guests.</p>
               <p>And if the <hi>Reioynant</hi> had followed the course of Law in pleading, the Matters had been brought to a short issue: but that it seemeth he hath declyned (as we conceive) thinking that we would have Demurred for <hi>Multiplicity</hi> or <hi>Impertinency</hi> of Matter, and so not to have sent after him into the Country that his <hi>Reioynder</hi> may stick fast there, but we hope, we shall finde a convenient time and way to go or send after him in any thing, when he shall in like manner slide away before. And we desire him and his Adherents, to take heed of the verior of <hi>Francisco Spira,</hi> and his fearfull end, for not restoring of the evill gotten Goods catched into his clutches, who repented very farre, in acknowledging the same, as well as other Sinnes; as is shewed in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the <hi>Tract, pag.</hi> 36. at large, and by such Divines there mentioned, may any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be informed of things, of and concerning all which premisses we put, and referr our selves upon, and to the same Persons, Tryall, Judgement, and Consideration, as we havedon out <hi>Reply;</hi> hoping that God wil direct those most concerned in the premis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, to seek and desire their just right in the same, and no other after so serious conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and mature deliberation had thereof: In which we doubt not but God will give them his assistance and blessing.</p>
               <p>And whereas the <hi>Reioynant,</hi> hath iniuriously charged us and our Friends, with the confounding of Tythes; Upon the whole matter it appeareth that the <hi>Impropriators</hi> of late have confounded Tythes, in deteyning the greatest part of the same, from the Ministry and the poore, for which use they were first instituted, as is mentioned before by us, which we and our friends have a desire should be brought into Order: which we hope the God of all Order, will according to his good Will and pleasure accomplish in due time.</p>
               <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>